Register of the Vasilii Maklakov Papers, 1881-1956
Hoover Institution Archives
Vasilii Maklakov Papers,
1881-1956
57005
Maklakov, V. A. (Vasiliĭ Alekseevich), 1870-1957
25 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 envelope (11.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches and writings, reports, diaries, and clippings, relating to Russian foreign relations with France, the Bessarabian territorial question, the Russian Revolution, and Russian emigres in France after the revolution.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1957.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (26 reels).
Access Points
Refugees.; Russians--France.; France.; France--Foreign relations--Russia.; Russia.; Soviet Union.; Russia--Foreign relations--France.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Bessarabia (Moldova and Ukraine); Moldova.; Romania.; Diplomats--Russia.
Biographical Note.
1869 Born, Moscow, Russia. Son of A. N. Maklakov, Professor at Moscow University
1887-1894 Attended Moscow University. Was expelled for political activity but reinstated and received diploma in history
1896 Received law degree and began private law practice in Moscow Elected member of Moscow Law Society
1907 Elected as a representative of Moscow to Second State Duma and reelected to Third and Fourth Duma Active member of Kadet Party
1917-1924 Appointed Russian Ambassador to France by the Provisional Government at which post he remained until France officially recognized the Soviet Union
1924-1956 Headed the Emigre Committee and Central Office in France dealing with all matters relating to Russian emigres in France and the French Government Member of the Nansen International Office for Refugees in Geneva
1936 Author of Vlast' i Obshchestvennost' na zakate staroi Rossii
1949 Author of Rechi: sudebnyia, dumskiia i publichnyia lektsii, 1904-1929
1954 Author of Iz vospominanii
1957 Died, Lausanne, Switzerland
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1917-1925. (Box No. 1.)
  Autobiographical sketches and diaries. Arranged alphabetically by physical form.
- Correspondence, 1917-1956. (Box No. 2-15.)
  Personal and political correspondence, especially with colleagues in the political arena, including A. Kerenskii, B. Bakhmetev, E. Sablin, and others. Also includes official correspondence with French government officials regarding Russian and emigre matters. Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- Speeches and Writings, 1913-1954. (Box No. 15-16.)
  Books, speeches, public lectures and book reviews by V. Maklakov. Arranged chronologically by title.
- Subject File, 1881-1956. (Box No. 17-22.)
  orrespondence, essays and printed matter related to Russian Embassy business, including negotiation at Paris Peace Conference on the question of Bessarabia and Boris Savinkov and Russkii Evakutsionnyi Komitet v Pol'she. Also includes writings by V. Maklakov and other material related to Russian emigre affairs in France, especially during World War II. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Clippings, 1917-1956. (Box No. 23-25.)
  Includes clippings of writings by V. Maklakov, especially in Russian emigre press, and notebooks of clippings dealing with Russian and emigres affairs, arranged for V. Maklakov by subject.
- Oversize File, 1914-1917. (Box No. 26.)
  Cartoons, map, posters, and flags related to World War I. Arranged alphabetically by physical form.
- Photograph, 1932. (Photo File.)
  Portrait print of F. Rodichev.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1917-1925
  - Autobiographical writings, n.d. Typescript (Box 1.)
    - General (Folder 1)
    - Appointment as ambassador to France (Folder 2)
  - Biographical essay, n.d. Rosa Vinaver (?) (Folder 3)
  - Diaries
    - Index (Folder 4)
    - Undated (Folder 5-6)
    - 1917 (Folder 7)
    - 1918
      - January-July (Folder 8)
      - August-December (Folder 9)
    - 1919
      - January-May (Folder 10)
      - June-December (Folder 11)
    - 1920
      - January-April (Folder 12)
      - May-December (Folder 13)
    - 1921
      - January-May (Folder 14)
      - June-December (Folder 15)
    - 1922 (Folder 16)
    - 1923 (Folder 17)
    - 1924 (Folder 18)
    - 1925 (Folder 19)
  - Miscellany, 1943-1945. Typescript (Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1917-1957
  - General (Box 2.)
    - French
      - Undated (Folder 1)
      - 1918-1925 (Folder 2)
      - 1926-1929 (Folder 3)
      - 1931-1945 (Folder 4)
    - Press. Correspondence with miscellaneous journals and press organizations, 1921-1928 (Folder 5)
    - Russian. Unidentified correspondents
      - Undated (Folder 6)
      - 1919 (Folder 7)
      - 1920-1922 (Folder 8)
      - 1941-1955 (Folder 9)
  - Aldanov, Mark
    - Undated. Also includes undated fragments (Folder 10)
    - 1929-1940 (Folder 11)
    - 1945 (Folder 12)
    - 1946-1947 (Folder 13)
    - 1948 (Folder 14)
    - 1949 (Folder 15)
    - 1950 (Folder 16)
    - 1951. Includes letter of Mark Aldanov to Abram Al'perin (Folder 17)
    - 1952
      - January-February (Folder 18)
      - March-December (Folder 19)
    - 1953
      - January-May (Folder 20)
      - June-December (Folder 21)
    - 1954
      - January-July (Folder 22)
      - August-December (Folder 23)
    - 1955 (Folder 24)
    - 1956
      - January-October (Folder 25)
      - November-December (Folder 26)
      - Material related to the celebration of Aldanov's 70th birthday (Folder 27)
    - 1957 (Folder 28)
  - Astrov, Nikolai, 1919-1933 (Folder 29)
  - Bakhmetev, Boris (Box 3.)
    - Undated (Folder 1-2)
    - 1919 (Folder 3)
    - 1920
      - Jauary-February (Folder 4)
      - March-April (Folder 5)
      - May-June (Folder 6)
      - August-Sept (Folder 7)
      - October (Folder 8)
      - November (Folder 9)
      - December (Folder 10)
    - 1921
      - March-April (Folder 11)
      - May (Folder 12)
      - June-July (Folder 13)
      - August (Folder 14)
      - September (Folder 15)
      - October (Folder 15)
      - November (Folder 17)
      - December (Folder 18)
    - 1922 (Box 4.)
      - January (Folder 1)
      - February (Folder 2)
      - March (Folder 3-4)
      - April (Folder 5)
      - May (Folder 6)
      - August (Folder 7)
      - October-November (Folder 8)
      - November (Folder 9)
      - December (Folder 10-11)
      - Printed matter and typescript reports included in the correspondence (Folder 12)
      - Letters addressed to B. Bakhmetev by others including Lieut.-Gen. A. Denikin (Folder 13)
    - 1923
      - January (Folder 14)
      - February (Folder 15)
      - March (Folder 16)
      - April (Folder 17)
      - May (Folder 18)
      - June-July (Folder 19)
      - September (Folder 20)
      - October (Box 5., Folder 1)
      - November (Folder 2)
      - December (Folder 3)
    - 1924
      - January (Folder 4)
      - February-March (Folder 5)
      - April-June (Folder 6)
      - August-December (Folder 7)
    - 1925 (Folder 8)
    - 1926 (Folder 9)
    - 1927
      - January-March (Folder 10)
      - April-July (Folder 11)
      - August-December (Folder 12)
    - 1928
      - February (Folder 13)
      - August-September (Folder 14)
    - 1929
      - February-May (Folder 15)
      - October-December (Folder 16)
    - 1930 (Box 6.)
      - January-March (Folder 1)
      - April-September (Folder 2)
    - 1932-1939 (Folder 3)
    - 1945-1946 (Folder 4)
    - 1947-1948 (Folder 5)
    - 1949-1951 (Folder 6)
  - Bayssellance, (?), 1929-1938 (Folder 7)
  - Bernatski, Mikhail, 1920 (Folder 8)
  - Berthelot, Henri, General, 1925 (Folder 9)
  - Boncour, J.-Paul, 1927-1931, re SHaliapin (Folder 10)
  - Boyer, Paul, Institut d'Etudes Slaves, 1918-1945 (Folder 11)
  - Bunakov-Fondaminskii, Il'ia, 1924-1940 (Folder 12)
  - Bunin, Ivan and Vera, 1951 (Folder 13)
  - Buisson, F., Ligue Francaise Pour la Defense des Droits des Hommes et du Citoyen, 1919-1924 (Folder 14)
  - Bure, (?), 1922-1932 (Folder 15)
  - Cambon, Jules, 1919-1927 (Folder 16)
  - CHebyshev, Aleksei, 1923 (Folder 17)
  - CHebyshev, Nikolai
    - Undated-1922 (Folder 18)
    - 1923 (Folder 19)
    - 1924 (Folder 20)
    - 1925 (Folder 21)
    - 1926-1935. Includes clipping of article, "Makulatura kak eksport. Kniga Trotskago." (Folder 22)
  - Clemenceau, Georges, 1918 (Folder 23)
  - Dillon, E., 1922-1928 (Folder 24)
  - Dimitriev, V., Capt., 1921 (Folder 25)
  - Duvernoy, Georges, 1921-1943 (Folder 26)
  - Duvernoy, Jane, n.d. (Folder 27)
  - Eisenmann, Louis and Le Monde Slave, 1925-1926 (Folder 28)
  - Elkin, Boris
    - 1945 (Folder 29)
    - 1946 (Folder 30)
    - 1947 (Box 7., Folder 1)
    - 1948 (Folder 2)
    - 1949 (Folder 3)
    - 1950 (Folder 4)
    - 1951 (Folder 5)
    - 1952 (Folder 6)
    - 1953 (Folder 7)
  - Fernand-Laurent, (?), 1940 (Folder 8)
  - Filosofov, Dmitrii, 1921. Includes copies of letters from Filosofov to others (Folder 9)
  - Fisher, Henry, 1934. Describes Russian Political Conference and Russian Political Delegation, 1919-1920 (Folder 10)
  - France
    - Chambre des Deputes and Senat. Correspondence with members, 1917-1940 (Folder 11)
    - Ministere des Affaires Etrangeres, 1919-1939 (Folder 12)
  - Gertsena, Natal'ia, 1936 (Folder 13)
  - Golder, Frank, 1928 (Folder 14)
  - Gol'dshtein, Moisei, 1920-1931 (Folder 15)
  - Gomelia, Leontii, 1920 (Folder 16)
  - Grenard, (?), 1933 (Folder 17)
  - Gruzenberg, Oskar and Vestnik Russkago IUridicheskago Obshchestva, Zakon i Sud (Box 8.)
    - Undated-1928 (Folder 1)
    - 1929-1930 (Folder 2)
    - 1934-1935 (Folder 3)
    - 1936-1940 (Folder 4)
  - Gul', Roman, 1949 (Folder 5)
  - Gurevich, G., n.d. (Folder 6)
  - Haumant, E., 1923-1929 (Folder 7)
  - Hebertot, Jaques, Theatres des Champs-Elysees, 1922 (Folder 8)
  - Herbette, Jean, Le Temps, 1922 (Folder 9)
  - Herve, Gustave, La Victoire, 1918 (Folder 10)
  - Karpovich, Mikhail
    - Undated-1946 (Folder 11)
    - 1947-1953 (Folder 12)
  - Kerensky, Aleksandr
    - Undated fragments (Folder 13)
    - Undated (Folder 14-16)
    - 1918-1920 (Folder 17)
    - 1945 (Folder 18)
    - 1946 (Folder 19)
    - 1947. Includes Kerensky 's speech "Russia and the United States". Typescript (Folder 20)
    - 1948 (Folder 21)
    - 1949 (Folder 22)
    - 1950 (Folder 23)
    - 1951 (Folder 24)
    - 1952 (Folder 25)
    - 1953 (Folder 26)
    - 1954 (Folder 27)
    - 1955 (Folder 28)
    - 1956 (Folder 29)
  - Kizevetter, Aleksandr, 1923-1929 (Box 9., Folder 1)
  - Kokovtsev, Vladimir, Count
    - 1924 (Folder 2)
    - 1927-1941 (Folder 3)
  - Kolchak, Aleksandr, Admiral, 1919. Signed by Prince L'vov et al. of Russian Political Delegation (Folder 4)
  - Kolchak, Sofiia, 1920 (Folder 5)
  - Konovalov, Aleksandr, 1920 (Folder 6)
  - Krivoshein, Aleksandr, 1920 (Folder 7)
  - Kurlov, Pavel, Gen., 1923 (Folder 8)
  - Kuskova-Prokopovich, Ekaterina
    - Undated
      - Fragments (Folder 9)
      - Before 1950 (Folder 10)
      - After 1950 (Folder 11)
    - 1922 (Folder 12)
    - 1923
      - January (Folder 13)
      - February (Folder 14)
      - March (Folder 15)
      - April (Folder 16)
      - May (Folder 17)
      - June (Folder 18)
      - August (Folder 19)
      - September (Folder 20)
      - October (Folder 21)
      - November-December (Folder 22)
    - 1924
      - January (Folder 23)
      - February (Folder 24)
      - March-May (Folder 25)
      - June (Folder 26)
      - August-September (Folder 27)
      - November-December (Folder 28)
    - 1925 (Folder 29)
    - 1926 (Folder 30)
    - 1927-1928 (Folder 31)
    - 1929 (Box 10., Folder 1)
    - 1930-1931 (Folder 2)
    - 1932-1935 (Folder 3)
    - 1936-1938 (Folder 4)
    - 1944-1945 (Folder 5)
    - 1946 (Folder 6)
    - 1947 (Folder 7)
    - 1948 (Folder 8)
    - 1949 (Folder 9)
    - 1950 (Folder 10)
    - 1951 (Folder 11)
    - 1952 (Folder 12)
    - 1953 (Folder 13)
    - 1954 (Folder 14)
    - 1955 (Folder 15)
    - 1956 (Folder 16)
    - 1957 (Folder 17)
  - Lebey, Andre, 1931-1932 (Folder 18)
  - Margerie, A. de, 1917-1918 (Folder 19)
  - Marsal, Francois, 1919-1929 (Folder 20)
  - Mel'gunov, Sergei, undated-1955 (Folder 21)
  - Mercure de France, 1922 (Folder 22)
  - Meyendorff, A., 1948 (Folder 23)
  - Miliukov, Pavel, 1918-1939 (Folder 24)
  - Millerand, A., 1918, 1920 (Folder 25)
  - Millington-Drake, E., 1925-1928 (Folder 26)
  - Morin, Louis, 1931-1932 (Folder 27)
  - Nabokov, V., 1922 (Folder 28)
  - Neratov, Anatolii (Box 11.)
    - 1919 (Folder 1)
    - 1920 (Folder 2)
  - Nicolaevsky, Boris, 1944-1951. Includes essay by V. Maklakov re Russian emigres in Paris during World War II, 1945. Typescript (Folder 3)
  - Niessel, A., General, Mission Militaire Francaise en Pologne, 1920 (Folder 4)
  - Noailles, Comtesse de, 1918-1930 (Folder 5)
  - Noulens, J., 1920-1938 (Folder 6)
  - Obolenskii, Vladimir, Prince
    - Undated-1949 (Folder 7)
    - 1950-1952 (Folder 8)
  - Paleologue, Maurice, 1922-1924 (Folder 9)
  - Pankhurst, Emmeline, 1918-1919 (Folder 10)
  - Paraf, Victor, 1926-1933 (Folder 11)
  - Payot, E. (?), 1927 (Folder 12)
  - Petit, E., 1920-1930 (Folder 13)
  - Protopopov, Evgenii, 1920 (Folder 14)
  - Rodichev, Fedor, 1919-1932. Includes copy of Maklakov speech on capital punishment (Folder 15)
  - Rodicheva, A., 1932-1954 (Folder 16)
  - Romanovskii, Ivan, Lieut.-Gen., 1919 (Folder 17)
  - Sablin, Evgenii
    - Undated fragments (Folder 18)
    - 1919 December-1920 May (Folder 19)
    - 1935 (Folder 20)
    - 1936
      - January (Folder 21)
      - February (Folder 22)
      - March (Folder 23)
      - April (Folder 24)
      - May-November (Folder 25)
    - 1937 (Folder 26)
    - 1938-1939 (Folder 27)
    - 1943-1944 (Folder 28)
    - 1945
      - January-February (Folder 29)
      - March-July (Folder 30)
      - August-December (Folder 31)
    - 1946 (Box 12.)
      - January-May (Folder 1)
      - June-December (Folder 2)
    - 1947 (Folder 3)
    - 1948 (Folder 4)
  - Sablina, Nadezhda
    - 1936 (Folder 5)
    - 1937
      - May-September (Folder 6)
      - October- December (Folder 7)
    - 1938
      - January-May (Folder 8)
      - June-September (Folder 9)
      - August-December (Folder 10)
    - 1939
      - January-May (Folder 11)
      - June-August (Folder 12)
    - 1940-1949 (Folder 13)
  - Savinkov, Boris. See also Subject File/ Russkii Evakuatsionnyi Komitet v Pol'she (Box 13.)
    - 1919-1920. Includes copy of letter to Winston Churchill (Folder 1)
    - 1921-1922. Includes "Pro memoria" and other material re Russkii Evakuatsionnyi Komitet v Pol'she and activities of Boris Savinkov (Folder 2-3)
  - SHtrandtman, Vasilii, 1935 (Folder 4)
  - SHul'gin, Vasilii
    - Undated-1921 (Folder 5)
    - 1922 (Folder 6)
    - 1923
      - January-March (Folder 7)
      - April-December (Folder 8)
    - 1924
      - February-May (Folder 9)
      - June-December (Folder 10)
    - 1925-1926 (Folder 11)
    - 1927-1928 (Folder 12)
    - 1929
      - February (Folder 13)
      - March-April (Folder 14)
      - May-December (Folder 15)
    - 1930 (Folder 16)
    - 1931-1939 (Folder 17)
  - Stakhovich, Mikhail
    - Undated-1918 (Folder 18)
    - 1919-1923 (Folder 19)
  - Struve, Aleksei, 1936-1950. Includes letters of Gleb Struve and Arkadii Struve (Folder 20)
  - Struve, Petr (Box 14.)
    - 1919-1920 May (Folder 1)
    - 1920 August (Folder 2)
    - 1920 September-1921 January (Folder 3)
    - 1923-1927 (Folder 4)
    - 1931 (Folder 5)
    - 1937-1940 (Folder 6)
  - Thibaut, M., La Revue de Paris, 1924 (Folder 7)
  - Thomas, Allen, 1918-1927 (Folder 8)
  - Tkhorzhevskii, Ivan
    - Undated-1936 (Folder 9)
    - 1937-1951 (Folder 10)
  - Tolstaia, Aleksandra. Also includes correspondence of Tolstoy Foundation Inc.
    - Undated-1939 (Folder 11)
    - 1944-1946 (Folder 12)
    - 1947-1955 (Folder 13)
  - Tolstaia, Tat'iana, 1917-1951 (Folder 14)
  - Tolstoy, Il'ia, undated-1919 (Folder 15)
  - Treadgold, Don, 1948 (Folder 16)
  - Trubetskoi, Nikita and Vladimir, Princes, 1949 (Folder 17)
  - Tyrkova-Williams, Ariadna
    - Undated-1919 (Folder 18)
    - 1921-1922 (Folder 19)
    - 1923-1943 (Folder 20)
    - 1944-1955 (Folder 21)
  - Ughet, Sergei, 1923-1932 (Folder 22)
  - Vilmorin, M. de, 1919 (Folder 23)
  - Vinaver, Evgenii, 1936 (Box 15., Folder 1)
  - Vinaver, Maksim, 1919-1924 (Folder 2)
  - Vinaver, Roza, 1937-1945 (Folder 3)
  - Vol'skii, Nikolai, undated-1954 (Folder 4)
  - Vrangel', Petr, Baron, 1920-1921. Includes letter signed by M. Girs et al. (Folder 5)
  - Weiller, Lazare, 1919-1924 (Folder 6)
- Speeches and Writings, 1913-1954
  - Untitled essays and fragments of text, n.d. Typescript unless otherwise noted (Box 15.)
    - Allied intervention in Russia (Folder 7)
    - Bolshevik power and the Civil War (Folder 8)
    - Franco-Russian relations (Folder 9-10)
    - German question (Folder 11)
    - Land question (Folder 12)
    - Miliukov. Reply to his review of Maklakov's memoirs (Folder 13)
    - Rasputin (Folder 14)
    - Rubenstein, Mikhail and his appointment to the Office International Nansen (Folder 15)
    - Russia-History
      - French (Folder 16-20)
      - Russian (Folder 21-23)
    - Tolstoy, L., artist and philosopher (Folder 24)
    - Trubetskoi, Petr, Prince. Reminiscences about him (Folder 25)
    - "Zemgor" and Russian humanitarian organizations in Germany (Folder 26)
    - Miscellany, n.d. Holograph (Folder 27)
  - Lecture to "Comite National des Etudes Sociales", n.d. Typescript (Folder 28)
  - Lecture about Nekrasov, n.d. Typescript draft (Box 16., Folder 1)
  - "O Peterburge", speech, n.d. Typescript draft (Folder 2)
  - "Paragraphes de A. K.", n.d. Typescript (Folder 3)
  - "Pered vtoroi Dumoi", n.d. Printed excerpt from an unpublished book (Folder 4)
  - "Po povodu knigi B. Nol'de", n.d. Review of B. Nol'de, L'Alliance franco-russe. Printed copy (Folder 5)
  - "Rech' o Moskve", n.d. Handwritten and typescript drafts (Folder 6)
  - Review of A. Pares, Fall of the Russia Monarchy, n.d. Typescript draft (Folder 7)
  - Review of Fenin book, n.d. Typescript draft (Folder 8)
  - Speech at Kokoshkin Jubilee, n.d. Typescript draft (Folder 9)
  - "Spasitel'noe predosterezhenie. Smysl dela Beilisa", 1913. Typescript. Also includes correspondence re trial (Folder 10)
  - "L'etape actuelle du bolchevisme", 1922 May and "La crise du bolchevisme", 1922 November
    - Printed copies, Mercure de France. See also Correspondence/Mercure de France (Folder 11)
    - Correspondence received by author especially from French politicians (Folder 12)
  - "La Russie de 1900 a 1917", La Revue de Paris, 1924. Printed copy. See also Correspondence/M. Thibaut, La Revue de Paris (Folder 13)
  - Speech at centennial of Pushkin's death, 1932. Typescript draft (Folder 14)
  - Vlast' i Obshchestvennost' na zakate staroi Rossii, 1936. Illiustrirovannaia Rossiia
    - Correspondence (Folder 15)
    - Reviews (Folder 16)
  - Note re Stalin-Hitler Pact, 1939
    - Typescript, 1939 (Folder 17)
    - Correspondence with representatives of the French government, 1939-1940 (Folder 18)
    - Review by S. Lianozov, 1940. Rossiiskii Torgovyi Promyshlennyi i Finansovyi Soiuz (Folder 19)
  - Pervaia Gosudarstvennaia Duma, 1939
    - Clippings (Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1940-1948 (Folder 21)
  - "Sovetskaia vlast' i emigratsiia", Russkie Novosti, 1945. Printed copy. See Subject File/Ob"edinenie Russkoi Emigratsii dlia sblizheniia s Sovetskoi Rossieii
  - Essays re relationship between Russian emigration and Soviet Union, 1945-1946(?). See Subject File/Ob"edinenie Russkoi emigratsii dlia sblizheniia s Sovetskoi Rossieii/Reports
  - Vtoraia Gosudarstvennaia Duma, 1946
    - Clippings (Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Folder 23)
  - "Ereticheskie Mysli". Correspondence, 1947-1949 (Folder 24)
  - Rechi: sudebnyia, dumskiia i publichnyia lektsii, 1904-1926, Paris, 1949. Izdanie iubileinago komiteta 1869-1949
    - Correspondence (Folder 25)
    - Reviews (Folder 26)
  - Iz vospominanii, 1954. Izdatel'stvo Imemi CHekhova
    - Correspondence (Folder 27)
    - Radio broadcast "Osvobozhdenie". Text of transmission. Typescript (Folder 28)
    - Reviews (Folder 29)
- Subject File, 1881-1956
  - Agafonov, V., Akademik V. I. Vernadskii, n.d. Printed copy (Box 17., Folder 1)
  - Bessarabia
    - Orders and official announcements, 1918. Typescript and printed copies
      - Romanian authorities (Folder 2)
      - Sfatul Tserii (Moldavian Republic) (Folder 3)
    - Paris Peace Conference and the League of Nations file
      - Correspondence of A. Krupenskii
        - 1918-1919 (Folder 4)
        - 1919 (Folder 5)
        - 1920-1921 (Folder 6)
        - 1922 (Folder 7)
      - Reports, policy statements and other material related to the conflict in Bessarabia, 1920-1922. Typescript and handwritten
        - General (Folder 8)
        - Bessarabian delegation
          - General (Folder 9-11)
          - Appeals to President W. Wilson (Folder 12)
        - Delegation Russe a Paris (including L'vov, Prince et al.) Addresses to the president of the Paris Peace Conference, July-November 1919 (Folder 13)
        - Romanian delegation (Folder 14)
    - Printed matter
      - General
        - Bessarabie. Introduction Historique, n.d. (Folder 15)
        - Sorok deviatoe Ocherednoe Benderovskoe Uezdnoe Zemskoe Sobranie, n.d. (Folder 16)
        - Ustav Bessarabskago Soiuza KHristianskikh Prikhodov Obshchin i Organizatsii, 1917 (Folder 17)
      - Clippings and typescript excerpts from press, 1918 (Folder 18)
      - Propaganda leaflets of revolutionary parties, n.d. (Folder 19)
    - Protests against abuses by Romanian authorities (Box 18.)
      - General (Folder 1-4)
      - Tikhon, Patriarch of Russia, 1918. Printed copy (Folder 5)
    - Reports and other material related to the Romanian occupation of Bessarabia. Typescript and handwritten, 1917-1920
      - General (Folder 6)
      - Agriculture
        - General (Folder 7)
        - Soiuz Zemel'nykh Sobstvennikov. Miscellaneous material, including reports and correspondence (Folder 8-11)
      - Economy (Folder 12)
      - Elections (Folder 13)
      - Intelligence (Folder 14)
      - Judiciary (Folder 15)
      - Military
        - General
          - 1916-1917 (Folder 16)
          - 1919 (Folder 17)
        - Obshchestvo bessarabtsev prozhivaiushchikh v Petrograde i ego okrestnostiakh, 1917. Reports and miscellaneous material related to the mission of Col. V. Krikopulo. Typescript (Box 19., Folder 1-3)
        - Vooruzhennye Sily IUga Rossii (V.S.IU.R.)
          - General. Miscellaneous material re evacuation of White Army to Romania (Folder 4)
          - General Staff, 1919. Reports. Typescript (Folder 5)
          - Kupidonov, S., Lieut., 1919. Report. Typescript and handwritten (Folder 6)
        - Vserossiiskii Voenno-Moldavskii Kongress, 1917. Miscellaneous material, including reports and protocols of meetings. Typescript (Folder 7)
      - Press. Includes letters to the editor (Folder 8-9)
      - Zemstvo and other organs of local government (Folder 10-11)
    - Statistics re ethnic composition of Bessarabia, 1912. Handwritten (Folder 12)